<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Full and true account of the landing of the late King James II in Ireland with a particular relation of his voyage ...</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 10 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 2 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A40568</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing F2307</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34443</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14438711</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14438711</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102338</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A40568)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102338)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1058:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Full and true account of the landing of the late King James II in Ireland with a particular relation of his voyage ...</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>1 sheet (2 p.)   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for R. Baldwin ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Imprint from Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Imperfect: pages stained and with print show-through.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12</date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102338:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A Full and True ACCOUNT Of the LANDING of the Late King James II. IN IRELAND. WITH A particular Relation of his Voyage, And Manner of RECEPTION, AND OF The SHIPS, MEN, MONEY, and ARMS, Which he hath brought along with him from <hi>France.</hi>
            </head>
            <floatingText type="license" xml:lang="eng">
               <body>
                  <opener>
                     <dateline>
                        <date>
                           <hi>March</hi> 22. 1688/9.</date>
                     </dateline>
                  </opener>
                  <p>Imprimatur.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>James Fraſer.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </body>
            </floatingText>
            <p>
               <hi>THat the World may be aſſured, that the late King</hi> James <hi>it now landed in</hi> Ireland, <hi>I ſhall not only give a particular Account of his Arrival there, but alſo of his Journey from the Court of</hi> France, <hi>to the Port of</hi> Breſt, <hi>and like<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſe of his Voyage thence to</hi> Ireland, <hi>and of the Ships, Men, Money, and Arms, which the</hi> French <hi>King hath ſent along with him for his Aſſiſtance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 25th of the laſt Month, <hi>New Stile,</hi> the late King <hi>James</hi> went from St. <hi>Germains</hi> to <hi>Peris,</hi> and there heard Maſs in the Metro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>politan Church of that City, where he was received by the Arch-biſhop at the head of the Chapter, and received the Sacrament at the hands of the <hi>Abbe Perfait,</hi> Canon of the ſaid Church. He afterwards dined with the Count <hi>de Lauz<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> on whom that Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing before he went to Maſs, he conferr'd the Honour of the Order of the Ga<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er Dinner he went to the Palace of <hi>Orleans,</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>o viſit and take leave of Madamoiſelle of <hi>Orleans,</hi> Madam the Great Dutcheſ of <hi>Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cany,</hi> and Madam of <hi>Guiſe.</hi> In the Eve<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing he went to the Court at <hi>Verſailles,</hi> to take leave of the <hi>French</hi> King, and return'd that Night to his late Queen at St. <hi>Germains en Lay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 27th the <hi>French</hi> King went to St. <hi>G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mains,</hi> to take leave of the late King of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 28th. early in the Morning, all thing<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> being ready for the late King's Journey to <hi>Brest,</hi> he took leave of his late Queen and the Child, all preſent being in Tears at his departure, the late King not excepted. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e travelled in a Calaſh, accompanied by the Marſhal Duke <hi>de Luxembourg,</hi> and Count <hi>de M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lly,</hi> as alſo by the Count <hi>de Aveux,</hi> the laſt <hi>French</hi> Embaſſadour in <hi>Holland,</hi> and now appointed to go along with the late King of <hi>England,</hi> in Quality of Embaſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour Extraordinary from the <hi>French</hi> Ki<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>g. He wen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> guarded by ſome <hi>French</hi> Horſe, and preceded and accompanied by divers <hi>Engliſh, Scotch</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>cers. The ſame day the late King got to <hi>Orleans,</hi> where he was lodged in the Houſe of the Sieur <hi>de Creit,</hi> Intendant of the Province, who met him a League and a half with his Coaches; the Citizens were in Arms, and complimen<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> him in a Body. The Intendant entertain'd him magnif<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cently at Supper; And the next Morning, b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing the Firſt of <hi>March,</hi> after ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving heard Maſs, he continued his Journey, and arrived that Night at <hi>Tours,</hi> where <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e was received and entertain<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d in like manner,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102338:2" rendition="simple:additions"/> by the Marqueſs <hi>Raſilly,</hi> Lieutenant General.</p>
            <p>The 2d, after having heard Maſs, he went and lodg'd that Night at <hi>Angers,</hi> and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards continued his way towards <hi>Nantes</hi> and <hi>Roch-Bernard,</hi> where he was magnifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cently received and treated by the Duke <hi>de Chau<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Govern<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ur of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ritany.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he 5th of <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>h</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nſtant, <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>w St<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> the late King arriv<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the Even<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>g at <hi>Brest,</hi> accompanied by the Perſons aforeſaid, as alſo by the Marſhal <hi>d' Eſtrees,</hi> who met and recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved him at <hi>Lanveoc,</hi> three Leagues off of <hi>Brest,</hi> with a Frigat and a Galiot, and moſt of the Boa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>longing to the Ships. He <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>as ſaluted as <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſed <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>long by <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ll <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Gu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of the Caſtle and Ships. The Coun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> Beth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ne,</hi> Chief of the Squadron, and the Sieur <hi>de C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeau,</hi> Intendant of the Sea, received him at his landing; where he was alſo received by the Biſh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>on,</hi> clo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ed Po<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap>ically at the head of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>gy; he pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>hrough <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> double Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> of C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>zens, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> wer<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ranged <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Arms on b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>es the S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ets, to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gings pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for him. He ſupped in Publick, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving at his Table the Duke of <hi>Berwick,</hi> the Marſhal <hi>d' Eſtrees,</hi> and the General Sea-Officers, with thoſe General Land-Officers which the <hi>French</hi> King ſent to accompany him to <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The 6th he went to ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Ship<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, and went on board the St. <hi>Michael,</hi> commanded by the Sieur <hi>Gabaret,</hi> Chief of the Squadron, as alſo on board another Man of War, commanded by the Sieur <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſo Chief of a Sq<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>adron, and in the Evening he viſited the Magazins of the Sea-Anchal. There <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ready in that Port Fourteen <hi>French</hi> Men of War, Three Fireſhips, and Seven Frigats, to Convoy the late King, as alſo a ſufficient number of Ten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and Veſſels of Burden; to tranſport Land-Forces, Arms and Ammunition.</p>
            <p>On the 7th, the Wind coming fair, the late King <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>barque <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> board the Str <hi>Michael,</hi> where he no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> done entered the Cabin but the Wind turn'd Northerly, he lay on board all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> and the Wind continuing contrary, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the 8th <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>our, land th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>re remain'd till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>; the Wind preſenting fair al ſecond <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, about Noon that day, he went on board <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> ſame Ship, and about 4 weighed Anchor, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nd <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for fall. About 12 at Night, being juſt got out of the Bay of <hi>Brest,</hi> the Wind <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>opped about Southerly, and oblig'd them to come to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Anchor, wher<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> they remain'd till <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> next <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, and t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>h'd into the Harbour.</p>
            <p>On the 14th the Wind preſented fair a third time, but being Eaſterly, and hearing ſome <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tch</hi> Men of War were approaching, they deferr'd putting to Sea. That Night they <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ceived advice, that there were neither <hi>Engliſh</hi> nor <hi>Dutch</hi> near them, and that the Coa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> was clear; nevertheleſs they deferr'd ſetting ſail till <hi>Thurſday,</hi> being the 17, <hi>New Stile,</hi> when the Wind being turn'd South-Weſt, fair for <hi>Ireland,</hi> and againſt the ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proach of any Ships from the <hi>Do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> they put to Sea a third time, the Wind proved wave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring, and ſo retarded their paſſage, that it was the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of this Month before they made ſight of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Being that day come near the Bay of <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſale,</hi> the Wind chopp'd contrary, and oppos'd their Approach or Entrance for above thirty hours, ſo that they were all that time forced to keep out at Sea, during which time they put forth <hi>Engliſh</hi> Colours; then the Wind turn'd favourable, and they advanc'd within the Bay, havin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> taken dow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Engliſh</hi> a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d put fo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th the <hi>F<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ench</hi> Colour<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and ſent a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oat on <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>cre to give the Town of <hi>Kingsale</hi> notice that it was the late King that was coming. Whereupon the Magiſtrates, Inhabitants, Officers and Soldiers in the Tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> gathered together and put themſelves in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eadineſs to receive t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> late King; which wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> perfo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>m'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, by all tha<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> were <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Papi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>s, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th great <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>lacrity, who floc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked to the Water-ſide and Huzza'd his Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, whilſt the Governour of the Royal Fort or Citadel ſaluted his Arrival with a treble diſch<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ge of the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>non, as a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>o b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>e Muſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kete<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>, as alſo Rin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ing of B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Bonfire<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> whe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Healths we<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> drank u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nees, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>fuſion of all Heretick<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nemies <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> their True Catholick King</hi> James. Notice of whoſe Arrival being forthwith given to the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> at <hi>Dublin,</hi> a ſufficient Guard was quickly ordered on the Road betwixt <hi>Kingsale</hi> and that City.</p>
            <p>The next day the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> King having heard Maſs, and <hi>Te Deum</hi> being ſung for joy of his Arrival in that Kingdom, and having recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved the Sacrament at the hands of an <hi>Iriſh</hi> Jeſuit, he was by the Tow<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> entertain'd at Din<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner. That Night he went to a Perſon of Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>y's Houſe an <hi>I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iſh</hi> man, attended by four <hi>French</hi> General Officers, and about Two hundred ſubaltern Officers ſtayed behind in the Town, with moſt of the <hi>Engliſh, Scotch,</hi> and <hi>Iriſh</hi> Forces; and the Souldiers (who 'tis thought are about Twelve hundred, with Arms for as many more, and about Four hundred thouſand Crowns in Money re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>main'd on board, it not being then re<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>ved whether they ſhould ſail forward for <hi>D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>lin,</hi> or land them there.</p>
            <p>On <hi>Thurſday</hi> the 14/<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> Inſtant, the late King being recovered of the Indiſpoſition cauſed by the Sea, ſet forward for <hi>Dublin,</hi> where he arrived on <hi>Saturday</hi> following being the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> of this Month, being met and received by the Earl of <hi>Tyrconnel</hi> ten miles from <hi>Dublin,</hi> who conducted him thither, having cauſed all the Forces there to be drawn up at the entrance into the Town, who ſaluted the late King's Arrival with three Vollies of Shot The Lord Mayor, Aldermen, and Comm<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Council alſo met Him in their Formalitie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> The Streets were lined with the <hi>Iriſh</hi> Li<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Guard even to the Caſtle-gate, where the la<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> King was conducted and lodged. The P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>piſts Inhabitants ſhouting, the Souldie<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Muskets diſcharging, the Bells ringing, an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> at Night Bonfires in all parts of the Town.</p>
            <p>The next day being <hi>Sunday,</hi> there wa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſinging of <hi>Te Deum,</hi> and Proceſſions for joy and a multitude of Maſſes ſaid for the Ad<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vancement of the Catholick Cauſe; to t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> great Terrour of all the Diſarmed Proteſtan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> there and thereabouts.</p>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="colophon">
            <p>
               <hi>London:</hi> Printed for <hi>R. Baldwin,</hi> near the <hi>Black Bull</hi> in the <hi>Old-Baily.</hi> 1689.</p>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
